okay this is the second lecture on
determinants there were only three with
determinance that's a fascinating small
topic inside linear algebra you used to
be determinants were the big thing in
linear algebra was the little thing but
they th those changed that situation
change now determinance is one specific
part a very neat little part and my goal
today is to find a formula for the
determinant it'll be a messy formula so
that's why you didn't see it right
away but if I'm given this n byn Matrix
then I use those entries to create this
number the determinant so there's a
formula for it in fact there's another
formula
a second formula using something called
co-actors so you you have to know what
co-actors are and then I'll apply those
formulas for
some some matrices that have a lot of
zeros away from the three
diagonals okay so I'm shooting now for a
formula for the
determinant you remember we started with
these three
properties three three simple properties
but out of that we got all these amazing
facts like the determinant of ab equals
determinant of a times determinant of
B but the three facts
were oh how about I just take 2 by tws
let can I I know because everybody here
knows the determinant of a 2X two Matrix
but let's get it out of these three
formulas okay so here's my my two 2 x
two Matrix I'm looking for a formula for
this determinant a b c
d okay so property one I know what to do
with the
identity right property two allows me to
exchange rows and I know what to do then
so I know that that determinant is one
property2 allows me to exchange rows and
know that this determinant is
minus one and now I want to use property
three to get everybody to get everybody
and how will I do that okay so remember
that if I keep the second row the
same I'm allowed to use linearity in the
first
row and I'll just use it in a simple way
I'll write this Vector
AB as a z
plus 0
B so that's one step using property
three linearity in the first row when
the second row is the same okay but now
you can guess what I'm going to do next
I'll because I'd like to if I can make
the matrices diagonal then I'm clearly
there so I'll take this one now I'll
keep the first row fixed and split the
second row so that'll be an a
Z and I'll split that into a
c0 and keeping that first row the same a
zero D I used for this part linearity
and now I'll whoops not plus because
I've got more coming this one I'll do
the same I'll keep this first row the
same and I'll split CD into c0 and z
d okay
now I've got four easy
determinants and two of them are
extremely well all four are extremely
easy two of them are so easy as to turn
into zero right which two of these
determinants are C are zero right
away the first guy
is zero why is he zero why is that
determinant
nothing forget
him well it has a column of
zeros
and by the well so one way to think is
well it's a singular Matrix oh for for
like 48 different reasons that
determinant is zero it's a singular
Matrix it has a column of zeros it's
it's dead and this one is about as dead
too column of zeros okay so that's
leaving us with this one now what do I
how do I know it's determinant following
the
rules well I guess one of the properties
that we actually got to was the
determinant of that triang of of that
diagonal matrix then so I I finally
getting to that determinant is the
ad and this determinant is
what what's this
one minus because I would use property
two to do a flip to make it
CB then property three to factor out the
b property C to factor out the c pro
property again to factor out the C and
that minus and of course finally I got
the answer that we knew we would
get but you see the
method you see the method because it's
method I'm looking for here not just a
2X two answer but the method of doing
now I can do
3x3 and
4x4s and any size so if you you can see
the method of taking each row at a
time so let's what what would happen
with 3x3 can we mentally do it rather
than I write everything on the board for
3x3 so what would we do if I had
3x3 I would keep rows two and three the
same and I would split the first row
into how many
pieces three pieces I'd have an A z0 and
A Z b0 and a 0 0 C or something for the
first
row so I would in instead of going from
one piece to two pieces to four pieces I
would go from one piece to three pieces
[Music]
to what would it be each of those three
would would it be
nine or
27 oh yeah I've actually got more steps
right I'd go to nine but then I'd have
another row to straighten out 27 yes oh
God okay let me say this again then if I
if it was 3 by3 I would separating out
one row into three pieces would give me
three separating out the second row into
three pieces then I'd be up to nine
separating out the third row into its
three pieces I'd be up to 27 three cubed
pieces but a lot of them would be zero
so now where when would they not be zero
tell me the pieces that would not be
zero now now I will write the nonzero
ones okay so I have this Matrix I I I I
think I have to use these start using
these double symbols here
because otherwise I could never do n by
end
okay okay so I split this up like
crazy
a bunch of pieces are zero whenever I
have a column of zeros I know I've got
zeros when do I not have zero when do I
have what is it that's Like These Guys
these are the survivors two survivors
there so my question for 3x3 is going to
be what are the survivors how many
survivors are there what are they and
when do I get a
Survivor well I would get a surviv
for example One Survivor will be that
one time that one time that one with all
zeros everywhere else that would be one
Survivor a11 0 0 0 a22 0 0 0
a33 that's like the a d Survivor tell me
another
Survivor what other thing oh now here
you see the clue now can should I just
say the whole clue that I'm having the
survivors have one entry from each row
and each
column one entry from each row and
column because if some colum is missing
then I get a singular
Matrix and it that that's one of these
guys see you see what happened with what
like this guy column one never got used
in z B 0
D so it's determinant was zero and I
forget it so I'm going to forget those
and just put so tell me one more that
would be a Survivor well the a11 well
here's another one A1 one
z0 now okay that's used up row row one
is used column one is already used so it
better be
zero what else could I have where could
I pick the guy which column shall I use
in row
two use column three because here if I
use column here I use column one in row
one this was like the column numbers
were one two three right in order now
the column numbers are going to be
one three column three and column
two so the row numbers are 1 2 3 of
course
the column numbers are some okay some
permutation of 1 2 3 and here they come
in the order
132 it it's just like having a
permutation
Matrix with instead of the ones with
numbers and and actually it's very close
to having a permutation Matrix because I
what I do eventually is I factor out
these numbers and then I have got so
that what is that determinant equ I
factor those numbers out and I've got
a11 * a22 *
a33 and what does this determinant equal
yeah now tell me that is we we're really
getting to the heart of these formulas
now what what is that
determinant by the laws of by by our
three properties I can Factor these out
I can factor out the a11 the a23 and the
a32 they're in separate rows I can do
each row
separately and then I just have to
decide is that plus sign or is that a
minus sign and the answer is it's
a minus why minus because there is one
row exchange to get it back to the
identity so that's a
minus now am I through no because there
are other
ways I what I'm really through
with what I've done what I've what I've
completed is only the part where the a11
is there but now I've got Parts where
it's
a12 and now if it's a12 that row is used
that column is used you see the idea I
could use this row and
column now that column is used that
column is used and this guy has to be
here
a33 and what's that what's that
determinant that's an a12 * an a21 * an
a33 and does it have a plus or a
minus a minus is right it has a minus
because it's one flip away from an from
the regular the right order the diagonal
order and now what's the other guy with
a with a a12 up
there I could have used this row I could
have put this guy
here and this guy
here right you see the whole deal now
that's an
a12
a23
a31 and does that go with a plus or a
minus yeah now that takes a minute of
thinking doesn't it because one row
exchange doesn't get it in line so what
what is the answer for this plus or
minus plus because it takes two
exchanges I could exchange rows one and
three and then two and three two
exchanges makes this thing A
Plus okay and then finally we have we're
going to have two more 0 0
a13 a21 0 0 0
A320 and one more guy 00
a13 0
a22 0 a 31 0 0 and let's put down what
we get from those an
a13 an
a21 and an a32 and I think that one is a
plus and this guy is a minus because one
exchange would put it would order
it and that's a
minus all right that has taken one whole
board just to do the 3X3 but do you
agree that we now have a formula for the
determinant which came from the three
properties and is must be
it and I'm going to keep that formula
that's a famous that 3x3 formula is one
that if if the camera will follow me
back to the beginning here I I get the
ones with a plus sign are the ones that
go down like down this way and the ones
with the minus signs are sort of the
ones that go this
way I won't make that
precise for two reasons one it would
flutter up the board and second
reason it wouldn't be right for
4x4s for 4x4 let me just say right away
4x4 Matrix the DI the the cross diagonal
the wrong diagonal happens to come out
with a plus
sign why is that if I have a 4x4 Matrix
with ones coming on the counter diagonal
that determinant is
plus
why why Plus for that guy because if I
exchange rows one and four and then I
exchange rows two and three I've got the
identity and I did two
exchanges so this down to this like you
know down toward Miami and down toward
La stuff is uh like 3x3 only
okay
but I do want to get now I don't want to
go through this for
4x4
I do want to get now the general formula
so this is what I refer to in the book
as the big
formula so now this is the big formula
for the determinant I'm I'm asking you
to make a
jump from 2x two and 3x3 to n
byn okay so this will be the big
formula
that the determinant of
a is the sum of a whole lot of
terms and what are those terms and and
is it a plus or a minus sign and I have
to tell you which which it is because
this came in in the 3X3 case I had how
many terms
six and half were plus and half or
minus how many terms are you figuring
for 4x4
if I
get two terms in the 2x two case three
ter six terms in the 3X3 case what's
that pattern how many terms in the 4x4
case
24 four
factorial why why four factorial this
would be a sum of N factorial
terms
24 120
720 whatever is after that
okay half plus and half
minus and where do those n factorial
terms come from this is the moment to
listen to this lecture where do those n
factorial terms come from they come
because the first the guy in the first
row can be chosen n
ways and after he's chosen
that's used up that that
column so the one in the second row can
be chosen n minus one ways and after
she's chosen that SEC second column has
been used and then the one in the third
row can be chosen n minus two ways and
after it's chosen notice how I'm getting
these personal
pronouns but I've run out
uh and I'm not willing to stop with
three by three so I'm just going to
write the formula down so the one in the
first row comes from some column Alpha I
don't know what Alpha
is and the one in the SEC I multiply
that by somebody in the second row that
comes from some different column and I
multiply that by somebody in the third
row who comes from some yet different
column and then in the N row uh I don't
know what I don't know how to draw maybe
Omega for last
and the whole point is then that that
those column numbers are different that
Alpha Beta gamma Omega that set of
column numbers is some
permutation permutation of 1 to
n it the N column numbers are each used
once and that gives us n factorial terms
and
when I choose a term that means I'm
choosing somebody from every row and
column and then I just mult like the way
I had this
from row and column one row and column
two row and column three so that what
was the alpha beta stuff in that for
that term here Alpha was One beta was
two gamma was three the permutation was
was the trivial permutation 1 two 3
everybody in the right order
you see that
formula it's you see why I didn't want
to start with that the first day Friday
I'd rather we understood the properties
because out of this formula presumably I
could figure out all these
properties how how would I know that the
determinant of the identity Matrix was
one for example out of this
formula why is if a is the identity
Matrix how does this formula give me a
plus
one you you see it right cuz CU almost
all the terms are
zeros which term isn't zero if if a is
the identity
Matrix almost all the terms are zero
because almost all the A's are zero it's
only the only time I'll get something is
if it's a11 * a22 * a33 only only the
only the permutation that's in the right
order will will give me something it'll
come with a plus sign and the determin
of the identity is one so so we could go
back from this formula and prove
everything we could even try to prove
that the determinant of a b was the
determin of a times the determin of B
but like next week we would still be
working on it because it's not uh uh
clear from if I took AB my God you know
the entries of a be would be all these
pieces well probably it's probably
historically it's been done but it won't
be repeated in 1806 okay it it would be
possible probably to
see um why the determin of a equals the
determin of a transpose that was another
like Miracle property at the end that
would that would that's an easier one
which we could find okay is that all
right for the big formula
I I could take then a typical let me do
an
example which I I'll just
create I I'll take a 4x4
Matrix I'll put some I'll put some ones
in and some zeros in okay let me I don't
know how many to put in to tell the
truth I I've never done this
before I don't know the determin of that
Matrix so like mathematics is being done
for the first time in in front of your
eyes uh what's the
determinant well a lot of there are 24
terms because it's
4x4 many of them will be zero because
I've got all those zeros
there maybe the whole determinant is
zero I mean is that a singular
Matrix
that that possibility definitely
exists I could I could uh so one way to
do it would be elimination actually that
would probably be a fairly reasonable
way to I could use elimination so I
could use go back to those properties
that and use elimination get down
eliminate it down do I have a row of
zeros at the end of elimination the
answer is zero I was thinking shall I
try this big formula okay okay let's try
the big formula how tell me one way I
can go down the
Matrix taking a one taking a one from
every row and column and make it to the
end so so I get something that isn't
zero well one way to do it I could take
that times that times that times that
that would be one and and and I just
said that comes in with what
sign plus that comes with a plus sign
because because that
permutation I've just written the
permutation about
4321 and one exchange and a second
exchange two exchanges puts it in the
correct
order keep walking away don't
don't okay we're executing a determinant
formula
here
uh as long as it's not periodic of
course if he comes back I
me no all right all right okay so that
would give me a plus
one all right are there any others well
of course we see another one here this
times this times this times this strikes
us right away so that's the order
three the order let me make make a
little different Mark here
24 and is that a plus or a minus
3214 is that is that permutation A Plus
or a minus
permutation it's a minus how do you see
that what exchange shall I do to get it
in the right order
if I exchange the one and the three I'm
in the right orders took one exchange to
do it so that would be a plus that would
be a minus one and now I don't know if
there are any more here let's see what I
could let me try again starting with
this uh now I've got to pick somebody
from oh yeah see you see what's
happening if I if I if I start there
okay column three is used so then when I
go to next row that I can't use that I
must use that now columns two and three
are used when I come to this row I must
use that and then I must use that so if
I start there this is the only one I get
and similarly if I start there that's
the only one I get so what's the
determinant what's the
determinant zero the determinant is zero
for that case because we we were able to
check the 24 terms 22 of them were zero
one of them them was plus one one of
them was minus one add up the 24 terms
zero is the answer okay well I didn't
know it would be zero because I wasn't
like thinking ahead I was a little
scared actually as that
uh that uh Apparition went by so and I
don't know if the
camera caught that so whether the rest
of the world will realize that I was in
danger or not we don't know but anyway
right I guess he just wanted to be sure
that we got the right answer which is
determinate zero and then that makes me
think okay the Matrix must
be the Matrix must be
singular and then if the Matrix is
singular maybe there's another way to
see that it's singular like find
something in its null
space or find a combination of the rows
that give zero and like what what what
combination of those rows does give
zero suppose I add rows one and rows
three if I add rows one and rows three
what I get I get a row of all ones then
if I add rows two and rows four I get a
row of all ones so Row one minus row two
plus Row 3 minus row four is probably
the zero row it's a singular
Matrix and I could find something in its
null space the same way that would be a
commin of columns that give zero okay
there's an example all right so that's
uh well that shows two things that shows
how we get the 24 terms and it shows the
great advantage of having a lot of zeros
in there
okay so we'll use this big formula but I
want to pick I want to go onward now to
co-actors onward to
co-actors co-actors is a way of breaking
up this big
formula that connects this n byn this is
an N byn
determinant that we've just have a
formula for the big
formula so co-actors is a way to connect
this n byn determinant to uh
determinants one
smaller one
smaller and the way we want to do it is
actually going to show up in this since
the 3X3 is the one that we wrote out in
full
let's let me do this 3 by so I'm talking
about
co-actors and I'm going to start again
with 3
by3 and I'm going to take the the exact
formula and I'm just going to write it
as
a11 this is the this is the determinant
I'm writing
I'm just going to say a11 * what a11 *
what and it's a11 * a22
a33 minus a23
a32 then I've got the
a one two stuff times something and I've
got the
a13 stuff times something do you see
what I'm doing I'm taking our big
formula and I'm saying okay
choose column that of the first row
choose column one and take all the
possibilities and those extra factors
will be what we'll call the co-actor co
meaning going with a11 so this in
parenthesis are these are in the
co-actors are in paren
a11 time
something and I figured out what that
something was by just looking back if I
can walk back here to the to the a11 the
one that comes down the diagonal minus
the one that comes that
way that's those are the two only two
that used
a11 so there they are one with a plus
and one with a minus
and now I can write in the I could look
back and see what used a12 and I can see
what used a13 and those would be the
co-actors of a12 and a
a13 before I do that what's this number
what is this
co-actor what is it there that's
multiplying
a11 tell me what a22 a33 minus a23 a32
is for this
what do you recognize
that do you
recognize let's see I could I'll put it
here there's the
a11 that's used column
one then there's the other factors
involve these other
columns this row is used this column is
used so this the only things left to use
are these and this formula uses them and
what's what's the
co-actor tell me what it is because you
see it and then then I I'll I'll be
happy you see what the idea of
co-actors it's a determinant of this
smaller
guy a11 multiplies the determinant of
this smaller guy that gives me all the
a11 part of the big
formula you see that this the
determinant of this smaller guy is a22
a33 minus a23
a32 in other words once I've used column
one and Row one what's left is all the
ways to use the other n minus one
columns and n- one rows one of
each all the other and that's the
determinant of the smaller guy of size n
minus one so that's the whole idea of
co-actors and we just have to remember
that with determinants we've got pluses
and minus signs to keep straight can we
keep this next one straight ah let's do
the next one okay the next one will
be when I use
a12 I'll have left so I can't use that
column
anymore but I can use A2 2 1 and
a23 and I can use a31 and
a33 so this one gave me A1 time that
determinant this will give me
a12 time this determinant a21
a33 minus
a23
a31 so that's all the stuff involving
a12 but have I got the sign
right is the determinant of that
correctly given by that or is there a
minus sign there is a minus sign I can
follow one of these if I do that times
that times that that was one that's
showing up here but it should have
showed it should have been a
minus so I'm going to build that minus
sign into the
co-actor
so so the co-actor so I'm put I put that
minus sign in here so because the
co-actor is going to be strictly the
thing that multiplies the the factor the
factor is a12 the co-actor is this is
the parenthesis stop in
parentheses so it's got the minus sign
built in and if I did if I went on to
the third
guy there would be this and this this
and this and it would take it
determinant it would come out plus the
determinant so now I'm ready to say what
co-actors are so this would be a plus an
a13 * its co-actor and over here we had
plus a11 times its
determinant but and there we had the a12
times its co-actor but the so the point
is the co-actor is either plus or minus
the
determinant so let me write that
Underneath Him what what is the what are
co-actors the
co-actor
of any number a i j let's
say this is this is all the terms in the
in the big formula that involve AI J
We're especially interested in
a1j the first row that's what I've been
talking about but any row would be all
right all right so the the what terms
involve AI J so it's it is it's the
determinant of the N minus one
Matrix without with row I column
J
erased so it's the it's a mat of size n
minus one with of course because I can't
use this row or this column
again so I have the Matrix all there but
now it's multiplied by A Plus or a minus
this is the co-actor and I'm going to
call that c i
j Capital I'll use Capital C just to
just to emphasize that these are
important and emphasize that they're
they're they're different from the A's
okay so now is it a plus or is it a
minus because we see that in this case
for a11 it was a plus for a12 I this is
i j it was a minus for this i j it was a
plus so any any guess on the rule for
plus or minus when we see those examples
I Jal 1 one or 13 was a plus
it sounds very like I + J odd or
even that that doesn't surprise us and
that's the right answer so it's a plus
if I + J is
even and it's a minus if I + J is
OD so if I go along Row one and look at
the co factors I just take those
determinants those one smaller
determinants and they come in order plus
minus plusus plus minus but if I go
along row two and and and take those
co-actors those subd
determinants they would start with a
minus because the 2 one entry 2+ one is
odd so the so like there's a pattern
plus minus plus minus plus if it was 5x
5 but then if I was doing a co-actor
then this sign would be minus plusus
plusus plus minus plus a sort of
checkerboard
okay okay those are the signs that that
are given by this rule i+ J even or odd
and those are built into the
co-actors
the thing is called a minor without the
before you've built in the sign but I
don't care about those build in that
sign and call it the co-actor okay so
what's the co-actor
formula what's the co-factor formula
then let me come back to this
board and say what's the co-actor
formula
determinant of
a is let's go along the first row it's
a11 times its
co-actor and then the second guy is a12
* its
co-actor and you just keep going to the
end of the row a1n * its
co-actor so that's co-actor form
along
Row
one and if I went along row I I would
those ones would be
I's that's worth putting a box
around that's the co-actor
formula do you see
that actually this would give me another
way I could have started the
whole
topic of determinants and some some
people might do it this choose to do it
this
way because the co-actor formula would
allow me to build up an N byn
determinant out of n minus one size
determinants build those out of n minus
2 and so on I could boil all the way
down to one by ones so what's the
co-actor formula for 2 by two matrices
yeah tell me that what's the co-actor
for so here's the here's the world's
smallest example practically of a of a
of a co-actor
formula okay let's let's go along Row
one I take this first guy times its
co-actor what's the co-actor of the one
one
entry D because you strike out the one
one row and column and you're left with
d then I take this guy B times its
co-actor what's the co-actor of
B is it C or it's minus C because I
strike out this guy I take that
determinant and then I follow the I + J
Rule and I get a a minus I get an odd So
it's b * minus
C okay it of course it
worked and the 3X3
works so that's the co-actor formula and
that is uh uh it's it's a good formula
to know and now I'm I'm I I'm I'm
feeling like wow I'm giving you a lot
of algebra to swallow here last lecture
gave you
properties now I'm giving you and by the
way those 10 properties led us to a
formula for the determinant which was
very important and I haven't repeated it
till now what was that the the
determinant is the product of the
pivots so the pivot formula is is very
important the pivots have all this
complicated mess already built in as you
did elimination to get the pivots you
built in all this horrible
stuff quite
efficiently then the big formula with
the N factorial terms that's got all the
horrible stuff spread
out and the co-actor formula is like in
between it's got easy stuff times
horrible stuff
basically but it's it shows
you uh how to get determinants from
smaller determinants and that's the
application that I now want to make so
may I
do one more
example so I remember the general
idea but I'm going to use this co-actor
formula
for a
matrix so here's going to be my example
it's I I promised in the in the course
in the lecture uh outline at the very
beginning to do an example and let me do
I'm going to pick triagonal
Matrix of
ones I could I'm drawing here the
4x4 so this will be The Matrix I could
call that
A4 but my real idea is to do n byn to do
them
all so a I could everybody understands
what A1 and A2 are yeah maybe we should
just do A1 and A2 and A3 just for so
this is A4 what what's the determinant
of A1 what the determinant of
A1 so so what's the Matrix A1 in this
formula it's just got that so the
determinant is one what's the
determinant of A2 so it's just got this
2 by two and its determinant
is
zero and then the
3X3 can we see its determinant can you
take the determinant of that
3x3
well that's not quite so obvious at
least not to
me being 3x3 I I don't know so here's
here's a good example how would you do
that 3x3 determinant we've got like n
factorial different
ways well three factorial so we've got
six ways okay uh I mean one way to do
it actually the way I would probably do
it being 3x3 I would use the complete
the big formula I would say I've got a
one from that I've got a zero from that
I've got a zero from that a zero from
that and this direction is a minus one
that direction is a minus one I believe
the answer is minus
one would you do it another
way here's another way to do it look
subtract Row three from I'm I'm just
looking at this 3x3 everybody's looking
at the
33 subtract Row three from row
two determinant doesn't change so those
become
zeros okay now use the co-actor formula
how's that how could how if this was now
zeros and I'm looking at this
3x3 use the co-actor formula why not use
the co-actor formula along that
row because then I take that number
times its co-actor so I take this number
let me put a box around it times its
co-actor which is the determinant of
that and that which is what
that 2x two Matrix has determinant
one so what's the
co-actor what's the co-actor of this guy
here looking just at this
3x3 the co-actor of that one is this
determinant which is 1
*
negative so that's why the answer came
out minus one okay so I did the 3X3 I
don't know if we want to try the 4x4
yeah that's I guess that was the point
of my example of course so I have to try
it sorry I'm in a good mood today so you
you have to stand for all the bad jokes
okay okay
so what was The
Matrix
uh okay now I'm ready for 4x4 who wants
this who wants to guess the the I I I
don't know frankly is 4x4 what's what's
the
determinant I plan to use
co-actors okay let's use co-actors the
determinant of
A4 is okay let's use co-actors of the
first row those are easier so I multiply
this number which is the convenient one
times this determinant so it's it's 1 *
the this 3x3 determinant now what is do
you recognize that
matrix it's
A3 so it's 1 times the determinant of
A3 coming along this row is a one time
this determinant and it goes with a plus
right and then we have this
one and what is its co-actor now I'm
looking at
now I'm looking at this 3x3 this 3x3 so
I'm looking at the 3X3 that I haven't
xed
out what is
that oh now it did A Plus or is it plus
this determinant this 3x3 determinant or
minus
it it's minus it right because this is
I'm starting in a one two position and
that's a minus so I want minus this
determinant but these guys are xed
out okay so I got a 3X3 three well let's
use co-actors
again use co-actors of the column CU
actually we could use co-actors of
columns just as well as rows because
because the transpose rule so I'll take
this one which is now sitting in the
plus position times its determinant oh
oh
hell what an oh yeah I shouldn't have
said hell because it's all right okay
one time
the determin what is that Matrix now
that I'm taking the this smaller one of
oh but there's a minus right the minus
came from from the fact that this was in
the one two position and that's odd so
this is a
minus one times and what's and then this
one is the upper left and it's the one
one position in its Matrix so plus and
what's this Matrix here do you recognize
that that Matrix
is yes please say it
A2 and we that's our formula for any
case
a of any size n is equal to the
determinant of a n minus one that's what
came from taking the one in the upper
corner the first co-actor minus the
determinant of a n minus 2 what we
discovered there is true for all
in I didn't even mention it but I
stopped taking co-actors when I got this
one why did I
stop why didn't I take the co-actor of
this
guy because he's going to get multiplied
by zero and no no use wasting time or
this one too the co-actor her co-actor
will be whatever that determinant is but
it'll be multiplied by zero so I won't
bother okay there is the
formula and that now tells us I could
figure out what A4 is now oh yeah
finally I can get
A4 because it's A3 which is minus1 minus
A2 which is zero so it's minus
one you see we're getting kind of
numbers that you might not have guessed
so our sequence right now is 1 0 -1 -
one what's the next one in the sequence
A5 A5 is this minus this so it
is zero what's
A6 A6 is this minus this which
is one what's
A7 I'm I'm going to be stopped by either
the time runs out or the board runs out
here okay A7 is this minus this which is
one
I'll stop here because time is out but
let me tell you what we've got what what
these determinants have this series 1 0
- one - one 0 1 and then it starts
repeating it's pretty fantastic these
determinants have period six so the
determinant of
a61 would be the determinant of A1 which
would be one okay I hope you likeed that
example a non-trivial example of a
triagonal
determin thanks see you on
Wednesday